You are listening to Ancient Faith Radio, Orthodox Christianity for today's world.
He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall, and
he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise.
and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge, but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons, and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to
see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
What do we permeate?
every day life with spiritual presence.
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung, host this live Colin show,
focused on enchantment in creation,
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Thanks for that voice of Steve.
Good evening, giant killers, dragon slayers,
wibbly, wobbly, timey whimers.
where this thing's at the Lord of Spear's spot.
I'm here. I'm father Steven D Young and I'm here with in Orthodox priest.
As Michael Horton called me today out out the old friend, Mike Horton.
That's right.
Yeah. So, uh, yes, uh, we are live.
And if you're listening to us live, you could call us at a five, two, three, seven, two, three, four, six.
And you could talk to us.
And we're going to get to your calls in the second half of the show and our very own
Our beloved, Matzyska Trudy the Tank Rector, will be taking those calls.
This episode is sponsored by Lord of Spigots, Fossets and Fixtures.
Are you concerned about what's really in your tap water?
Not just contaminants from the local superfund site or that time your cousin backed his
leaky jeep into the creek, but spiritual contamination.
Ever get the feeling like your morning coffee was looking back at you?
Or maybe that your eggs were having some hell boiled into them?
Well, we have this
bigot for you are all new Lord of Spigot's spiritual stones, filtration faucets, patent pending,
equipped with authentic umem and thumem-shaped purifiers.
Leave your tap water not just sparkling clean but so pure from demonic presence that you'd
think you were burning incense 24-7.
After you install one of these, your parish priest will be coming to you for holy water.
And with just one extra monthly payment of $29.9995, you can get the optional Aspergillum
boss at head, which will have all your treadcath friends to
planting a spurgis may.
Act now will throw in not just one,
but two, ancient faith branded
potholder and tea-cozy sets call now.
Lord of Spakets, Fots, its infixures.
Why are we throwing that super expensive
bone to the Western right?
I'm not gonna.
So, tonight, we're going to tackle a subject
that we've referenced many times
over the course of our now hundreds of hours
yacking on how to understand the
the incarnation of Christ in light of the bodily experiences of God in the Old Testament.
We've said in the past the body with which the Son of God walks in Eden or eats with Abraham
is the same body taken from the Virgin Mary. How can this be? Doesn't the second person
the Trinity only become man around two thousand years ago, but then what do we do with those
very material? It's not weird. Here's how. Okay. Yeah. Yeah. It's all going to work out
on the end everybody I promise.
leave yourself. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So how do we deal with those very material experiences
of God in the Old Testament? And, and this is the question I want to answer. Was Hamlet
fighting against Dossettism when he said, seems madame? Nay, I know not, seems.
I think he was opposed to women being involved in the art of tailoring.
I don't even know if you're thinking about it.
It was actually what was going on there.
Something has rotten.
I'm not sure if it's the
whole
room.
It's probably the
Lutafisk.
The whole charm of the place in
its cuisine north of there.
I know.
Yes.
And we have, by the way,
tuning in tonight, we've got
someone from Norway, someone from
Brazil, someone from
Bayon.
Who else?
Where else do you people
turning in from?
I'm sure you're all over.
the long leaf.
Pine. Oh, and somewhere over the rainbow in Kansas. Very nice. Very nice. Oh, one of our listeners says,
I'm not convinced Lord of spigots is real. Why would I do a commercial for something that's not real?
Yes. What have we ever lied to our audience? It's calling me a liar, apparently. Yes. How dare you,
Sir or bad.
Ooh, Manitoba.
Manitoba.
I've been to the Capitol of Manitoba.
It is like a playground, a free masonry.
I'm not even kidding about that, Manitoba.
Canada is a free mason conspiracy.
You've heard it.
Some from Texas.
Some from the spirits.
Don't believe their apologies.
They aren't sincere.
Oh, someone from Sweden.
We have a Swedish, so that's good.
Yeah.
So we have everyone from Scandinavia,
exceptedane.
Exceptedane.
Defint account as
I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. They speak a weird native
in or language. Florida Panhandle. Hello, Florida. Ontario. Hello, Ontario.
Yeah. All right. We got a number of countries tuning in.
Yeah. To hear us talk about what countries are tuning in.
So it's all very, it's all very circular in meta that you get here on the
Yeah, okay.
Yeah, you are super committed to this one being a shorter one too
That's how we start I know I
Think you are two minds about the whole things are all right. I accept my fate
Yeah, so
You brought up dacetism there at the beginning and that's where we're gonna start we're gonna start with heresies
Yes.
Just a few of the 1000 hairies practiced by a certain member of my parish.
I poor guy. It's been a while since he's called in.
It has. Yeah. He's been trolling a certain Protestant apologist on Twitter, I think.
Oh, yes.
Who I, yeah, instead of us on the phone.
Um, yeah.
But so really what we're talking about tonight, obviously, is under the subheading of Christology.
The title of the episode, I think most people didn't realize was kind of a question.
Yes, when in terms of how do we understand?
the relationship between Christ's incarnation and time and space. And so we're talking about the
incarnation and we're talking about Christology and one of the ways into early Christology is actually
to look at ancient heresies. Why? Yeah. Well, because in the controversy over, especially
very early heresies, right? We see something in the heretical movement. We see something
being denied. Yeah. And therefore on the other side, something being asserted. Yeah, right.
And so different sorts of heresies arise at different times based on...
what things are taken for granted, what things are seen as open for dispute.
An emphasis going one way will trigger an over emphasis going the other way that turns into something
heretical, advice versa.
Yes, sometimes you have the dueling heresies.
Right, the correction of that heretical move too far in one direction might lead to a count.
move in the other direction that then also needs to be corrected. Right? So we're starting
with what is arguably the very first Christological heresy. And by very first, we're talking about
into the first century beginning of the second century.
So we're dealing with nascent Christianity.
Yeah.
and factions within it.
Now, you can make a pretty good case
that the earliest Christian heresy
is some form of marcynism.
Marcynism is heretical on a bunch of counts.
Yeah, it's kind of a whole little,
it's not one idea, it's a whole set of stuff.
Yeah.
And it's not explicitly a crystallological problem.
Right.
I mean, there's a certain polyphiasum problem with Marseism.
Yeah.
But it's not strictly speaking,
Marseid did believe that Jesus Christ was the son
of the true God.
He just had another one running around.
So the other kind of contender
for earliest Christological heresy,
and why am I pausing to do this at the beginning?
I think we all know why.
Because if I don't do this there's gonna be like YouTube comments
Actually, we're gonna get a lot of facts. Yes, like the technically this other one, right? Okay
So tip those Fedoras everywhere. Oh, actually the Fedora tipping guy is not that image you usually get it's not actually Fedora
It is in fact a hat called a Trilby so
Just putting that out there
You have confirmed your title as the Earl.
of pedantry for this year. That's right. What podcast are we on? Yeah, right.
The other kind of contender for early Christmas and logical hours, you would probably be serentheanism.
I guess I know Serenthus is somebody you all think about every day.
Serentheanism is
sort of a version of what comes to be a larger category of heretical Christologies called
adoptionism.
Yeah, the idea that Jesus is a man and he gets sort of made God.
He gets adopted as the son of God.
Right.
That's where the adoption comes from, but just he's a man who is divinized in some way at
some point.
So that's a broad.
Obviously adoption is um is called adoption is um rather than being called after the name of a person
There's not a guy named adoptus who came up
It's it's called that because it covers this why so there were adoptionists who thought that that Jesus became the son of God at the resurrection
Right at different points, right, but syrithus in particular
taught that
that
Jesus
of Nazareth was just a man, but then at his baptism, the divine logos came and sort of
attached itself to him.
So you have, within the idea that the logos, the second person of the Trinity and Jesus
are different people, sort of who are connected.
connection happens after a certain period.
period in Jesus' life, this is actually the heresy for which the author of the last
temptation of Christ was excavated from the Greek Orthodox Church.
Yeah.
Fun fact.
By the way, we have someone, this might be our first time, I don't know, but we have someone
tuning in from New Zealand.
So hello, New Zealand person.
New Zealand person.
Yes, yes.
And also, I, someone said they were tuning in from Mexico.
I don't remember seeing Mexico.
before actually this might be our first first Mexican listener.
It's pretty good.
Other than the radio station, right?
Other than the radio station.
That's true.
But yeah.
Because I wonder like I wonder if they could hear me talking
quietly in the background of their music.
I'm sure you converted several of them.
It's possible.
It's probably.
Somebody on Twitter said I have converted more people to
Christianity than Pope Francis.
I'm sorry.
I wasn't sure where it is what even begin and even be yeah.
So I'm probably as meant as a compliment or a shot at Pope Francis.
I don't know.
It could be, you know, yeah.
Porquén on those does.
So Serenthus lived very early on.
Right.
the first begins.
Second century. So some people will say that, but serentheanism as such didn't sort of become
a significant movement. That's why, for example, if you've studied early Christianity, you've heard
of adoptionism and probably not of serentheanism, right? There isn't a big sort of movement surrounding
Whereas dostatism, right, even though it's also not named after a person, it's not named after
Okidok or something.
It is, it forms some kind of cohesive group.
And it says that there were some kind of congregation, some kind of communities that could be identified as dostatist communities.
Please.
by staining nations of Antioch amongst others.
And so yeah.
So he throws a lot of wonderful shade at them.
Yes. So what is dacetism?
Well dacetism comes from
everybody, you know, everybody always says it comes from the verb d'Aquel,
which means to see him, right?
Yeah. But there's a noun, doxa, that means seeming. Yeah, which is doxa.
Or the way something appears. Yeah, glory. I can also be an opinion. But opinion. But it's that group of
that group of Greek. Yeah. And we're related to the word dogma as well. Yes. And well, that doxa
is the one in orthodoxy.
Right, right, right.
But it needs to seem or to appear, right, or seeming or appearance if we're talking about the noun and the idea here is that
these are groups where they taught that
Jesus of Nazareth just appeared to be a human person, right?
They completely agree seem to be a human person they agreed that he's divine
But they're like, yeah, his humanity just kind of
a parent or seeming. That's the reason why St. Ignatius one points is they're the seeming ones. In
the words, those are the fakes. Yeah. So this is the end of the first beginning of the
second century. Now, by the way, I know we've beaten this hopefully to death, right? If
If not, here's round 18 of
That's right. We're going to exume this dead horse of one of us going after our 19th century
German friends and their view of evolution, the evolution of theology. And this is really the
power hypothesis. This is really Christology. Evolutionary Christology. We're going after this time
rather than the Trinity or what have you. But this idea, right?
which is still, especially if you pick up sort of out of date books,
you will still find touted that, oh,
in the first century, everyone believed that Jesus was just a man that he was a
prophet, that he was a human prophet, a human Messiah.
And then, you know, a little bit later, they started thinking he was like kind
of divine in some sense.
You may do it eyes.
that it's only when you get to like the fourth century that anybody thinks he's God.
Yeah, I mean, there's even, I mean, there's relatively recent books about this.
I think there's no one with titles like When Jesus Became God or something like that.
Well, relatives, we're old, Father Andrew.
We're seven, sevens, fathers.
You just like, referred to a recent book that came out 20 years ago.
Oh, no.
Yes.
I'm out of touch.
Yes, your Boards are trying to powder.
And Bart Urban who wrote that book
has changed his position since then.
Oh, there's also one by Gainin.
Two his credits.
I haven't read it.
Richard Rubenstein called When Jesus Became God.
But the Bart Urban,
and then there was a response book
that a bunch of evangelicals wrote
called When God Became Jesus.
Very good.
Oh,
Urban's book is How Jesus Became God.
Oh, How Jesus Became God.
Yeah, yeah.
There you go. So but he's now changed. Now I still disagree with him. For example, he basically thinks St. Paul was an Aryan.
Oh, but that's
that's closer than what he used to say, right? He used to say St. Paul just thought Jesus of Nazareth was a human. So,
just kind of moving to the right direction. But
the problem and I think this is part of I mean I can't speak for him I don't know
his mind
but I think part of why he changed his mind is just,
it seems pretty obvious that if one of our earliest,
if not the earliest,
crystallological heresies,
consists of groups of people believing
that Jesus is divine and not human,
that that whole evolutionary thing kind of falls apart.
Yeah, I mean, it's amazing.
I mean, it's astonishing.
It's breathtaking to me.
How many people have this view?
And yet all most all of the early arguments over Christology for centuries are not about
whether he's God or how he's God.
It's whether and how he's human.
Yes.
You know, even, yeah, even Aryanism is a version of that.
Except that he's divine.
Yes.
Right.
different sets that is correct. Yeah.
Right. So, I mean, this alone should totally flip that, right? Like,
hello, there were people at the end of the first century who Christians had to argue with,
to say, no, Jesus was human, not just divine. I don't know how you get from that fact,
Which they would acknowledge is a fact.
They don't deny that the Dostatists existed.
Yeah.
Right.
I don't know how you get from there to everybody
just thought he was a human Messiah,
and then gradually they started thinking
he was a word or divine.
It just doesn't make you can't hold those two things together.
Yeah.
I mean, you know, St. Ignatius who is literally a,
not even a second generation Christian,
like a half, a one and a,
1.5 generation Christian, right?
Friends of the apostles, yeah.
Yeah, he's with the apostles.
ordained by the apostles. He's a disciple of the apostle John, probably ordained by St. Peter.
He's our best earliest source for the not just the existence of the Dositist, but what they believe.
He's constantly arguing with them in his seven letters. Yeah. You know, these seven letters that
everyone agrees or legit.
Yeah.
And he's like, you're wildest liberal, right?
You're wackiest.
Protestant. Yeah. All agree that these letters are legit. He talks about the flesh of Jesus over and over and over and over again.
Like it's really something that he's really hammering on. Yeah. But also important human you guys. But also importantly,
he never does that at the expense of Christ being divine. Oh, absolutely not. Absolutely. He never says,
as though now hold your horses guys.
He's done.
divine he's actually human right or he's half and half. He's not that divine because he's kind
of human right. They are used passionately for Christ's humanity while also fully acknowledging
everything the dothatists want to say about Christ's divinity. But in some cases more.
Yeah and I mean and you know listen if you know if you don't believe us just take the time to read
his seven letters, you can read out log in the space.
of an hour. Yeah, you can read all seven of them in the space of an hour. Yeah. So there's
then this question of, well, okay, dositism, as we said, we're really just talking about
Christology, right? But I made the statement that Dostatism, unlike adoptionism.
that there were these actual communities, right?
Then this isn't just a category for lumping together
everybody whose version of Christology
doesn't hold the Christful humanity, right?
It's not just that.
Now it does become that a little bit later.
And in some sloppy scholarship,
like they'll refer to fourth and fifth century groups
as having a deacetic Christology, right?
Because their Christology is similar to this, right?
but the dosages proper.
are these groups, are these actual communities at the end of the first and beginning of the second centuries?
Now that means they have other beliefs too, right? Like they're not just gathering every day to talk about like that Jesus wasn't human.
Yeah, I mean, this is partly why synagnatious not only talks about their Christology, but also the fact that they won't receive the Eucharist together with them.
and he has this massive emphasis.
on worship being with the bishop.
I can't even go so far at one point as to say,
anyone who is not with the bishop
is a worshiper of the devil.
Like it's pretty strong language.
Right.
You know.
But these words nonetheless,
functioning communities, religious communities.
Yep, right.
We lose, I think we lose sight of that sometimes.
uh what we're talking
about these ancient heretical groups, like we think the Arians just sat around all day talking about
how the sun is not equal to the father. Like no, they had like liturgies and they read the Bible and
preached and like they had a whole thing going on. It's just they had this one one element very
wrong, right? And their theology. And that was reflected in places in their worship and in other
things right there was fallout from that but there were also
functioning communities and so
One of the questions then comes like well what what kind of communities were these?
Decedic
communities right and the default answer you'll get
From most
So the
The number of people actually studying dositism, right, like they wrote
their dissertation about dositism is relatively small, as with any other hyper specialization
in academia.
Yeah.
Right.
So, and in any hyper specialization in academia, you have tiers of literature, right?
So you have the books on dositism written by, you know, the handful of, you know, $130
paperback bril books written by the people who are scholars of dacetism. Right?
And they're talking about Dositis about one level. So when I say most scholarship, I'm not talking about that
Because that is like hyper nuanced and stuff, right like
These are guys off in a quarter discussing this stuff in excruciating detail, right?
I'm talking about your average when I say most scholarship. I'm talking about
Certain biblical commentaries on parts of the New Testament that will refer to Dositism
So, you know, Stanley.
Early Church History.
Yeah, exactly, exactly. They talk about the heresy of dacetism, right? What most of those kind of things will say is
They will basically treat dacetism as just well. These are nostics
Right now in one hand that's easy to do because nostic again is this big basket
Into which tons of groups get thrown
right and state urna is the second half
of the second century kind of uses this term,
nostics to bunch together the sathians and the valentines
and the surviving Marcy Knight groups and a whole
bunch of other groups to say, hey, they have these features
in common, right?
So we'll put them all in this basket as a way of talking
about them, right?
But it's not like the sathians and the valentines
or like in communion with each other or something.
No.
No, these are just sort of academic categories.
Right, this is just a big category.
So on one hand, you know, looping these
dissident communities into dosticism, right?
Like you're just saying, well, okay,
there's kind of similar in certain ways.
We're just gonna throw them in that basket.
But the problem is, the problem is once you do that,
Then
people make a whole bunch of assumptions about these dissent at communities.
Right? For example, the big thing that categorizes most of these
that causes them to get thrown into that basket is that there is a certain confusion of metaphysics.
and ethics, where they view matter as evil, right? And then spirit as good. And so yes, in most
sort of nostic schemes, they're all over the place because there's always different fractured
sex of narcissism.
They're not going to have anything like an incarnation of the Christ or the logos.
Sometimes in these doxic systems, the logos of the Christ and Jesus are three different
people.
It's kind of a mess.
It's wacky stuff.
There are three Jesus' and Manicannism, for example.
But the point being, yes, they all pretty much never have it in carnation because...
matter is evil, right? And so if they're holding some figure to be good and
divine, then it can't be encarned in matter because matter is evil, okay? But the
fact that their belief in matter being evil causes them to say that the
Christ just seemed to be a man doesn't mean that the Dossitists because they
He said Christ just seemed to be a man.
Thought matter was...
evil. Yeah, yeah. There are other reasons why you could think that, right? Now, why would you want to
bother just lumping the dothesis in with dothesis in many way? One might ask, right? Why not just
have a couple of lines in your textbooks saying the dothatists were groups of Christians who didn't
believe that Jesus was really a man, that he disappeared to be a...
Well, I just leave it there. Why are we putting the
Gnostic label on that? What's the purpose of categorizing
them with the Gnostic? Well, you have to understand is that
way back in the long ago time, when Father Andrew and I were
young and full of life and vigor, as opposed to now.
Back then, we were in the middle of what is now called the
third quest for the historical Jesus.
Yes
Which then turn out
so swell. Kind of old-hell stuff.
A quest story ever.
Yeah, like Indiana Jones at least found the thing he was looking for even if it got warehouse,
you know. Like, but at part of the agenda for some of the scholars involved in it.
a number of whom are now dead.
So we can speak ill of the knobs.
Um, like Robert Funk and,
Robert Funk was a wild dude, by the way.
He was the guy who started the Jesus seminar
and he had been like a boy Methodist preacher.
Look at his 11 and 12.
Oh, I, it's such a weird phenomenon.
He had been like a Hellfire and Brimstone boy preacher.
And yeah, yeah.
kind of had an effect on him.
negatively, religiously, that whole experience.
But the CERNG is never part of there and Marcus Borg is now deceased.
John Dominic Risson is still around and kicking.
Vice C is ever.
But part of the agenda of some of those folks
was they were trying really hard to make an argument
that narcissism priest...
ex seated Orthodox Christianity.
Yeah.
They really wanted to argue, especially funk,
that that narcissism was the original Christianity,
and it was actually Orthodox Christianity.
What we now call Orthodox Christianity,
that was a heretical offshoot of the original
monasticism.
And we will go into all the reasons why
of that. A lot of it.
had to do with non-understanding dosticism. But there was this kind of view, very boomer
horrific view, that somehow dosticism was like sexually liberated and gender and
egalitarian and all this stuff, which is absolutely not true. But that was
idea where as opposed to, you know, mean old crusty misogynist Christianity.
And so they made all kinds of arguments hypothesizing an early Aramaic
version of the Gospel of Thomas that we don't have that was written before the canonical
Gospels, on and on and on, right?
And so there was this impetus throughout that sort of movement to try to make Gnosticism
as early as possible.
The problem with this whole thing, of course, is that Gnosticism is a second century phenomenon,
a mid-second century phenomenon.
No. No. It is in the mid-second century an attempt to, in some cases, not all, sort of
sprinkle Christian terminology and symbolism across paganism and make this sort of
syncretistic hybrid. They do the same thing with Judaism. They do the same thing with
different forms of Eastern Relief.
and so far as they had access to it.
They're just sort of get sprinkled in syncretized
with Greco-Roman paganism, with Egyptian religion.
So really, that's what narcissism is.
It's this synchrotistic tradition within Greco-Roman paganism
in the mid-second century.
So by roping or looping
which actually did exist at the end of the first century
Into narcissism I make you get a kind of narcissism. Well look we just put narcissism back into the first century boys
We just need another 60 years or so and we're golden
Unfortunately, they couldn't manage to get narcissism back that 60 years it just didn't work
and it all fell apart.
Yeah, I mean, I was just...
I think it's partly because Christianity just isn't that well known yet, you know, by that point
that you get this sort of weird philosophical
speculation and
magic systems and whatever that is
Nosticism starting to mess with it.
Right, you know, let's see. They were trying to, of course, this is connected to a quest for the historical Jesus.
They were trying to mess with the historical Jesus.
Yeah, of course.
and turn Jesus into some kind of philosopher.
Sorcerer that yeah depending on and the real honestly the the
Even some of the participants now
Have kind of yielded to the analysis that when you go looking for the historical Jesus the Jesus you find looks a lot like you
At best it looks like an idealized version of you
Right like it looks like what you aspire to be
And so, yeah, even among the participants of the Jesus seminar and the third quest for
the historical Jesus, they all published their books on the historical Jesus and none of
agreed with each other about anything, hardly.
Which makes it real hard to argue that this is the product of like objective scholarly
research when everybody's conclusions are completely different.
in terms of some pretty basic things.
Right?
Well, so we rule this out.
We say like there's no reason to bring
nozzlesism into this discussion.
Right.
What else do we know about these
dissedic communities?
Well, I think one of the things that we know
that's been mostly treated as confusing
in the literature is saying
Ignatius makes some pretty clear references.
in the midst of talking about these
docentist groups, to them strictly
keeping the Torah.
Yeah.
As in like circumcision, the whole
Shabang, like keeping it as if
they were Jews.
Right.
And this, of course, like I said,
this gets treated as a problem in
the literature.
Because the literature, and again,
I'm not talking about the top end
and stuff from this
the hyper specialist, but I'm talking about the general literature.
General literature says, well, dothatism is nostec.
How does that fit with you have to be circumcised in the flesh and keep kosher?
Yeah, because why would nosticism care about that kind of thing?
Yes. Right. In fact,
nosticism tends to be kind of mercy and I they tend to really not like the old testament.
Yeah. Right.
So it doesn't make a lot of sense.
you get some, you read, start reading journal articles about this, you get some people proposing
things. You get a lot of people just ignore the stuff about Toriqy because it doesn't
make sense to them. You get some people proposing, well, maybe this is a Jewish-nastic group, right?
he's dealing with to try to like split the difference
Right. And there, there, there are some phenomena in the second century, second century.
Like I mentioned that you could kind of call Jewish noctisism.
But again, they're Jewish noctisism.
So there's like Judaism sprinkled across it, but they're not like Pharisees.
Yeah. They're not like they're not, you know, focused on keeping the Torah.
It's not with this is not a phenomenon within rabbinic Judaism.
Yeah.
Right, this is something else.
Let me propose there's a much simpler solution here.
Right, again,
flushed nostus is amount of the picture.
Why would a Jewish group?
Why would a Jewish group
that accepts Jesus as the Messiah?
Think that he wasn't human.
Well...
There's a lot of the offenities in the Old Testament, right?
Yeah.
God appears.
A whole bunch of times.
We've talked about a lot.
Go to our Christology episodes.
Our Old Testament Christology episodes.
Right?
God appears, shows up, does things, people see him in the Old Testament.
Seems to me, a much simpler solution that these Dostatists are groups of Jewish Christians
who believed that Jesus of Nazum...
was a theophonane, right? Like the Old Testament the
offonays and not an actual human being, right? And one can see how
from the perspective of the rest of Christianity, this would be a problem,
This would be a problem.
So...
Now early can we trace dothatism? Well, one of the things people will do with this, again in the literature is they'll say, well, are there anti-deceptic texts in the New Testament?
Are there places where we see, say in the epistles of the New Testament, where we see the
authors writing against dacetism or against ascetic community.
communities. Right? The answer to that properly speaking is no. Right? The technically correct
answer, that is the best kind of correct. There's no because those groups don't exist yet,
as the epistles are being read. But really, yes, in the sense that there are tax in the
testament which because of what they say right attack criticized refute
dacetism yeah yeah even though they weren't originally aimed at these groups
that didn't exist yet yeah right so in the same way that later the church
fathers could say oh this text is aimed at refuting dynatism well
Donate has lived in the...
the 4th century. Right. Right. Right. Right. So under the Apostles were like having visions,
there will be a heretic in the 4th century. I must refute him. Right. But things they wrote
apply to the things that Donatist got wrong. Yeah. When the fathers went looking for stuff
in the scriptures to express the faith that they believed in, this was stuff that they
point in it. Right. And so there's a whole series of tax here.
we're going to go through relatively quickly, relative for us.
That emphasize the fact that Jesus has specifically flesh but also bones, blood, human material
reality.
Okay, we're going to start with
Luke 2439. This is one of the post-resurrection appearances of Jesus. This is Jesus speaking. He says,
see my hands and my feet that it is I myself touch me and see, for a spirit does not have flesh
and bones as you see that I have. So he's this is after the resurrection. Yeah. Pretty straightforward.
Not a ghost. Yes. Still has this body. Now let me say, I'm not going to mention the person today
about a respect for the person.
person. But an intelligent person used this verse as kind of a weird proof text to argue
that Jesus after the resurrection didn't have any blood.
I know because it said flesh and bones.
Because it says flesh and bones. And the argument I guess is that as we're going to see a
little later flesh and blood would be the more common co-location, right? But it says
flesh and bones.
Allow me to suggest that if we read this whole verse again, see my hands and my feet that is on myself touch me and see
When you touch a person you don't feel their blood
Right, you feel their flesh and their bones
That they are solid and therefore not a spirit
Right Christ doesn't say
The fact that Christ doesn't say in that verse, cut me, do I not bleed?
There's second one for tonight.
There you go.
The fact that he doesn't say that doesn't mean he doesn't have blood, right?
That's a false conclusion to jump to.
But he does have blood.
So even after the resurrection here, this is emphasizing he still has his material body.
Yeah.
Okay.
John chapter 1 verse 14
and the word became flesh.
And dwelt among us, and we have seen his glory,
glory is of the only son from the Father,
full of grace and truth.
The famous prologue of John, the word became flesh.
Yes.
Yeah.
Acts chapter 2 verse 31.
He foresaw and spoke about the resurrection of Christ
that he was not abandoned to Hades,
nor did his flesh see cry.
corruption. This is important because again, let's talk about the resurrection. Right.
If Christ was just a spirit or a ghost, his flesh still would have seen corruption in the
grave. Yeah. Right. Or if it's just even after the resurrection. Yes. Left behind, there
be no point in mentioning that. Right. Yeah. Yeah. All right. St. Paul and Romans chapter
one verse three. This is continuing continuing a previous sentence concerning
his son who is
from David according to the flesh. So emphasizing that his descent from David is the way that everyone
else is descended from their ancestors. You know, he has a family tree. Yeah, just like humans. Yep. Yep.
So okay, same book Romans chapter 9 verse 5, to them along the patriarchs and from their race,
according to the flesh is the Christ.
Who is God overall, blessed forever, amen.
wait a minute. He is part of the Jewish ethney. God overall. Yeah. Yeah. Man. Right. But he is part of
the Jewish ethney here. Yeah. To the flesh from the patriarchs from their race or nation or yeah.
All right. Ephesians 2 verse 14 for he himself is our peace as being Christ who has made us both
one
and has broken down in his flesh the dividing wall of hostility.
And this is referring to this is referring to the crucifixion.
Yeah. So this is referring to his death,
according to the flesh in the flesh. Yeah. Okay, Hebrews 214. Since therefore, the children share
in flesh and blood. He himself likewise, particularly the same things that, through death, he might
destroy the one who has the power of death, that is the devil.
So he partook of flesh and blood, like the humans who he is saving.
And then emphasizing through death.
You know, he has that human body, therefore he can die.
Okay, first Peter chapter four, verses one and two,
Since therefore Christ suffered in the flesh,
Army
with the same way of thinking, for whoever has suffered in the flesh has ceased from sin,
so as to live for the rest of the time in the flesh no longer for human passions,
but for the will of God. So that's Christ suffering in the flesh, and so if we also suffer in the flesh,
joining our suffering to him, we cease from sin. So our time, again, in the flesh is no longer,
as he says, for human passions, but according to God's will instead.
Yep. Yep. Okay. First John 4, 2 by this, you know, the Spirit of God, every spirit that
confesses that Jesus Christ has come in the flesh is from God. Again, that emphasis on
it's pretty straightforward. The human body, exactly, exactly. All right. Our final
one, second John 1, 7, for many deceivers have gone out into the world, those who do not
confess the coming of Jesus Christ in the flesh.
Such a one is the deceiver and the anti-Christ.
That's the same thing in the negative sense.
Yeah.
Right.
So St. John, in those two epistles,
sets this up as the sort of shibbolath for discerning spirits,
is did Jesus Christ come in the flesh?
Yep.
And St. John is the one New Testament author
author who was alive at the end of the verse.
and who actually could have been dealing with something like Donatism.
Donatism, I mean, yes.
Or Donatism, yes.
Not Donatism.
Two centuries out.
Yeah, and despite what the Vetterable Beed says about first John Tubers too.
Donatism.
But yes.
Yeah, and again, Ignatius is his disciple, so they're connected very much together.
Right.
So I think...
I think texts like that are so familiar to us and the fact that yes Jesus is
human is so taken for granted by us. I think most most of our cultural and
American day, most of our cultural depictions of Jesus if they air air on the
side of.
human all too human right um yeah
and you know we're we're maybe a little more prone to lose sight of Christ divinity than likewise um
you know we've got people out of certain television network having visions of
Jesus played the saxophone over their beds at night.
We've got a lot of real.
bad paintings of Cuddly Jesus giving people and animals hugs. You know, yeah, but I
mean, you know, the people in first century Judea, they saw him. Right. Do wonders,
you know, more than any prophet had ever done. Right.
Greater stuff than any prophet had ever done. And as it says in the
the gospels, hundreds of people saw him raised from the dead.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, and you know on the war at least quasi scholarly level. No serious person
denies that Jesus existed as a human. Yeah. Then I'll reiterate that anyone who anyone
who comes to you and tells you that Jesus never existed is not a serious person. Right.
See Bart Irman's excellent book on the subject. Right. Let Bart explain to you why you're not
a serious person if you think Jesus never existed.
So, uh, still the offer's still good, by the way.
Yeah.
Parties are these dimly aware of my and this show's existence now.
We know.
And that we refer to as a friend of the show.
So if you hear this,
Bart, or someone passes it on to you,
you still have open invitation to come on the show at any time.
On our completely unironically,
time.
On our completely unironically.
right to talk about whatever. And the only person who has that is a friend of the show
burnerman. I say on the on the rest is history podcast most of their friends of the show
are all dead for centuries. So there's no danger of them coming on. Oh, who does? So, but
Yeah, so it doesn't.
It doesn't strike us when we read like that list and we can list more quotes. Trust me.
But those are just representative. When you read a list of quotes like that, the fact
that they keep talking about Christ's flash doesn't strike us. Okay. But if you just go
Do the Strongs concordance thing.
Look at how Flash has talked about a new testament.
The vast majority of uses of the term flesh are negative.
Yeah.
There is, for example, a distinction in St. Paul, where when he's talking about our physicality,
our material physicality, he talks about our body, and when he's talking about our sinful desires
and passions, he talks about our flesh.
Right? It's a Paul made some of those quotes about Christ that we just read.
or from sample.
St. Peter, right after talking about Christ suffering of the flesh, just talking about making no provision for the flesh, and its desires, right? On and on and on, right?
So it seems counterintuitive
that the apostles, the way they usually talk about flesh, human flesh,
flash that they would want to tribute that to Jesus because they're also
all completely clear that Jesus was not a sinner.
Yeah. Right.
So why would they do that?
Why would they use that term?
Why wouldn't they use some other term?
Right. Why would they do that?
Especially if everyone at the time agreed
he was a human person.
Why would you feel the need to keep pointing to the flesh?
Right.
It seems really weird because when you dig into it, clearly some people did not believe
it.
Right.
Yes.
And we're not saying they're necessarily already dostitists around, but again, where did dostitism
come from?
And what we find and what we've talked about before on the show in various contexts and
that we're going to be talking about more now in the second half is the
fact that by the time you get to the first century, within Second Temple Judaism, there is this
belief, a very firm solid belief expressed in various ways, that the Messiah, who is going to come,
is some kind of pre-existing divine or divinized being, the logos, the Son of Man, the Messiah.
This is being that already existed before coming as the
Messiah. Right? This is an idea that a whole lot of people have. But we'll revisit that.
You've heard us talk about this before, but we'll revisit it again and focus it on it.
Here in the second half coming up. Yeah, exactly. All right. Well, that's the first half
of this episode of The Little Spirits. We're going to take a short break and we'll be
right back. See you soon. Father Andrew Stephen, David and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back
in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a call
and 855
237-2346. That's 855-AF Radio.
The centuries after the Protestant Reformation brought about a radical reinterpretation
of the epistles of St. Paul, disconnected from any historical reality.
The Paul operated during his entire life as a faithful Pharisee within the Roman Jewish
world. In St. Paul the Pharisee, Jewish up
to all nations, by their Stephen D. Young surveyes Paul's life and writings,
interpreting them within the holy tradition of the Orthodox Church.
This survey is followed by D. Young's interpretive translation of St. Paul's
epistles, which deliberately avoids overly familiar terminology.
By using words and ideas grounded in 1st century Judaism,
D. Young hopes to unsettle commonly held notions and help the reader reassess St. Paul
in his historical context.
available now at store.AncientFace.com.
Again, that is store.AncientFace.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, thanks, boys, for Steve.
I was actually talking to the real Steve
the other day on the telephone.
He is more than you're applying to the voice of Steve is a fake.
No, he only seems no way.
That's the wrong half.
Yeah.
So well, before we dive into the second half, we actually do have someone calling from
Colorado.
It seems is it for the show, Bart Irman?
It's probably not.
Oh, probably not.
Yeah, it's Alec.
So Alec, welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Thank you so much for having me, father.
God bless you.
What's on your mind, Alec?
Well, long time fan, so thank you so much for taking the time.
A question that might be somewhat pertinent tonight, though, I guess we'd have to rewind time a little bit.
In the gospels, there are mentions of both the disciples and our Lord preaching the gospel.
And father, I've read your book on this topic.
And so I'm curious, what was the gospel they were preaching?
at that time before the crucifixion and resurrection
had happened.
I don't think we're as much getting into Jesus being
as open about his proclamation as being
carnated son at that time.
So what was the gospel they were preaching?
Yeah, I mean, the short version of it is simply
repent for the kingdom of God as at hand.
Right? It says this very explicitly,
the crisis preaching that gospel, John the Baptist
is preaching.
that gospel repent for the kingdom of God as at hand. Certainly all the things that Jesus was about
to do were, would not have been in the content of that necessarily, but that's the idea is that
that there's this conquest that is coming. And so, and Jesus is the conqueror, and so you need to
repent if you're going to be on board with what's coming. Right? So all the details are not quite
right there yet.
But the message is there.
And I mean, it's clearly effective.
People are repenting when John the Baptist breaches
that even before Jesus is on the public scene.
So yeah, I mean, that's what it is very basically.
It's really about you need to change your way of living
because the kingdom is coming
and this is how citizens of the kingdom live.
So that's the action item.
Sort of.
speak is repent because things are about to change. Everything's about to change. It's
at hand, as St. John says, the acts is laid to the root. So, yeah, I mean, they're not
saying Jesus has been crucified and risen from the dead yet. But of course, there are
points, there are points when Jesus tells that to his disciples, you know, one point where
Peter kind of says, you know, rebuke him, like stop saying that. That's weird.
But yeah, it's repent for the Kingdom of God as a hand.
Is there anything I left out there, Father?
Well, and I mean in context,
the Kingdom of God as a hand brings the whole prophetic
Corpus De Maul.
Right, for Jewish people.
So they understand this is referring to the day of the Lord
and they went, God will visit his people.
He will judge the heavens of the earth.
His enemies will be defeated.
So so say.
The kingdom of God is at hand and therefore you need to repent.
They would have understood it within that prophetic context.
This is about to happen.
Therefore now is the time to repent.
No more procrastinating, no more putting off.
This is about to happen.
It's not that the content of what Christ was about to do wasn't in it.
It was in it, but it would have been phrased and framed the way what Christ was going to
do this framed, for example, in Isaiah, right? Or in Ezekiel, right? So it would have
been described in that prophetic mode, right? And I think this is part of the reason why
there, you see the different reception between St. John the Forerunner and Christ, not by someone
like hered but
by the people.
Right?
St. John the Forerunner is still speaking in the terms they're used to hearing, but it's just
telling them that time is coming soon.
Yeah.
Right?
And that was a time that they were looking at with hope and fear, and he was telling them what they needed to do to prepare for it.
whereas especially when you get into the latter portion of Christ's ministry.
And he does start as Father Andrew said, he starts saying, oh, I'm going to go to Jerusalem and be crucified.
Oh, you know, this is going to happen. That's where people start going, whoa, hey, wait, time out. What? That's not what we're expecting. Wait.
Yeah. Right.
We thought the Christ remains forever. Yeah. Right. And so
that's where you start seeing people drift away and even some people becoming antagonistic.
to Jesus of the idea that he's the Messiah, right?
Within that context.
Yeah.
Is that clear things up there for you, Alec?
I think it does.
And I think would you maybe also say that in kind of foreshadowing
the ultimate triumph over the dark spiritual powers
with the resurrection and Holy Saturday,
do you have the casting out that's happening as well,
sort of, you know, paving the way for kind of the more polar.
or a fuller defeat that was soon to come.
Yes, although I mean, I would say that that's just like,
you know, the army has landed on the beach
and immediately begins shooting the enemy.
That's what happens with Jesus.
I mean, the exorcism, yes, they're not all quite wiped out yet,
but like the exorcisms are not just a foreshadowing.
It's the initial assault.
Right.
But also, exorcism was, we talked about this
at least one episode.
Exorcism.
was associated with the Davidic Messiah.
Yeah. In the sense that was there were a set of Psalms of David that were used for exorcism.
And that's likely connected to the fact that it's David who finishes wiping out the giant cleanse.
These are the ones who does the mop up.
And so there's a connection there.
with the Davidic Messiah also, which is why in the synoptic
gospel's Christ's exorcism activity is sort of particularly
important.
All right. Thanks for calling, Alec.
Thank you so much, fathers.
Both of your work has been very helpful in leading me toward
the church. So keep up the good work.
Thank God. Pray for us, please.
Okay. Continuing on with the second half.
Yeah, so okay, you said at the end that the first half that there is this idea of a pre-existent
spiritual Messiah that existed in Second Temple Jewish thought. Easy for you to say.
I know, I know. So where is that coming from? Why are they interpreting things that way?
Right, so well, and some of this is review of things we've talked about, but
But there is CRO Testament Cresault.
episodes which we're not going to review in total here obviously there's more than
than well we were there three or four so yeah so there is this second Yahweh
figure in the Hebrew Bible there is and that's defined in various ways one of
them is we talk about there is this sort of blanket state.
repeated many times over that no one can see the God of Israel, no one can see
capital G God, no one can see Yahweh and live. And then we have a whole bunch of
examples of people seeing Yahweh and living. Yeah, wait a minute. Right. And sort of
the locus classicus of this that really gives us, that really problematizes
is it for us is reading through Exodus 30, chapter 33.
where we're told that Moses speaks to God face to face the way a man speaks to his friend,
it's literally mouth to mouth in the Hebrew. And then nine verses later, nine verses later,
Moses asked God to show him his glory, his co-vote. And God says, you cannot see me alive. And it's like,
it. Like you don't even have to turn a page like it. Like so clearly there's a Yahweh
that can be seen in a Yahweh that you can't see. Right. And so this is one of the basic
breakdowns. And this is this is what Saint John is commenting on in his prologue, not the
verse we read previously, but when he says, no one has seen God at any time. Right. But
depending on your Manning Sript edition.
the unique God or the unique son who was in the bosom of the father has made him known.
Right.
And again, St. John is not retconning the Old Testament.
He's saying all those times when people saw God, who they were seeing was the son, the
logos.
Yeah.
Right.
But that bosom of the father language is important there too.
That's language when you read Second Temple Jewish texts that talk about a priest.
existed Messiah. So take for example, in the book of Enoch, first edic in the book of parables,
when it talks about the son of man, right, this pre-existing Messiah figure, who identifies
as the Messiah, who is going to come into the world and be the Messiah, it identifies
this figure as being sort of hidden in the bosom of the Father.
from essentially eternity past, from before the creation of the world.
And he was then going to be revealed on earth as the Messiah. And so that language,
that traditional language is what St. John is referring to there when he talks about him being
in the bosom of the Father. So this is a very common thing as you read through.
and they don't all agree about who this figure is.
is going to be. I'm not saying they all believed in Orthodox Christian Christology exactly
in Second Temple Judaism. That is not at all what I'm saying. Because what they're doing
is they're reading prophecy, they're reading the Hebrew Scriptures and they're trying
to figure it out. They have this shape and they have this shadow and they have this outline
and they have these types and from that they're trying to figure this out.
And then the reality of that, of course, becomes clear once, you know, that figure actually reveals
himself at the person of Jesus of Nazareth. But they have this outline and there are these different
titles like this out of man referring to the Daniel text, right, which we've talked about before on the show.
And we've talked about before on the show how one of the ways that this
idea that there are these two persons of Yahweh gets reflected in the Targums is that the
the Arabic Targums will in these places where someone sees or interacts directly with God,
it's the word Memorah, which means word. Right, so instead of you know,
So it's sort of saying...
God appeared to Abraham and will say the word of God appeared to Abraham.
This is where the logos language comes from in St. John and in Filo.
Logos being Greek.
It's the D'Barrio way in Hebrew.
So all this, like I said, we've talked about this a bunch of times on the show.
in different contexts, especially those Old Testament Christology contexts.
Why are we talking about it again here?
Well, so what we were talking about,
I don't imagine we have a ton of
dosatist listeners.
Call in.
Correct me if I'm wrong.
Yes, call it if you're a dosatist, I guess.
I'm telling the wrong.
Feel free to call in about whatever.
But,
so, you know,
You know, what we're going through.
there. Yes, Christ came with a flesh, Christ, fleshed blood. Yes, that was probably non-controversial
to 99.999% of our readers, right, our listeners. And probably what we were just talking about,
because we've spent dozens of hours at this point on this show talking about Old Testament
Christology and theophonies.
People have probably most of our listeners who have listened to that.
If tonight's not your first night, you're probably at least somewhat on board with those ideas of the second power in heaven and this kind of thing, being an idea that already existed in second-table Judaism before Christianity.
Here's where it gets problematic.
A lot of these appearances of God in the Old Testament, these theophonies, these appearances
that we're going to say are the second person of the Trinity that are the Son, right?
are the logo.
that are the Son of Man, right?
That are ultimately Christ, right?
A lot of these appearances,
even though they're in the Hebrew Scriptures,
even though they're the Christian Old Testament,
when this figure appears,
he has bodily physicality.
Yeah.
Yes, bodily physicality that does things
and that functions.
Yeah, which you have to ask then.
So what is that body?
Is he incarnate more than once?
I mean, like, you know, you have to come up with some way of understanding
what's going on with these old testament appearances that are not just appearing.
They're touching.
We've got some examples.
Yeah.
Right.
We've got some specific examples here.
One of them just in general, we're not going to read the whole chapter.
But remember, of course, Genesis 3.
God comes walking in the garden.
Yep.
And more importantly than just like that imagery, right?
The verb, right?
God is moving.
You know, you can say, well, walking shouldn't be literal there.
Except,
Adam and Eve,
or man and woman at that point, hear him walking.
Yeah.
What are they hearing?
Yeah, they hear him.
walking, crunch, crunch on the ground. Right? Physicality.
Yep. Yep. All right. We're going to cover part of Exodus
chapter 24. So I'm going to read through this. It's the first
18 verses. Then he, that's God said to Moses, come up to the
Lord, you and Aaron, Nehdaab and Abihu and 70 of the elders
Israel and worship from afar. Moses alone shall come near to the Lord, but the others
shall not come near, and the people shall not come up with him. Moses came and told the
people all the words of the Lord and all the rules, and all the people answered with one
voice and said, all the words that the Lord has spoken, we will do. And Moses wrote down
all the words of the Lord. He rose early in the morning and built an altar at the foot
of the Mount, and twelve pillars, according to the twelve tribes of Israel. And he sent
young men of the people of Israel who offered burnt offerings and sacrificed peace offerings
of
to the Lord, and Moses took half of the blood and put it in basins, and half of the blood
he threw against the altar. Then he took the book of the covenant and read it in the hearing
of the people. And they said, all that the Lord has spoken, we will do, and we will be obedient.
And Moses took the blood and threw it on the people and said, behold, the blood of the
covenant that the Lord has made with you in accordance with all these words. Then Moses
and Aaron, they dabbing a behoo, and seven of the elders of Israel went up, and they saw
the God of Israel.
was under his feet as it were a pavement of sapphire stone, like the very heaven for
clearness. And he did not lay his hand on the chief men of the people of Israel. They
beheld God and ate and drank. The Lord said to Moses, come up to me in the mountain
and wait here that I may give you the tablets of stone with the law and the commandment which
I have written for their instruction. So Moses rose with his assistant Joshua and Moses
Jesus went up into the mountain of God, and he said to the elders,
Wait here for us until we return to you, and behold, Aaron and Huwre are with you.
Whoever has a dispute, let him go to them."
Then Moses went up on the mountain, and the cloud covered the mountain.
The glory of the Lord dwelt on Mount Sinai, and the cloud covered it six days.
And on the seventh day, he called to Moses out of the midst of the cloud.
Now, the appearance of the glory of the Lord was like a devouring fire on the top of the
mountain in the sight of the people of Israel.
As the cloud entered the cloud and went up on the mountain, and Moses was on the mountain.
40 days and 40 nights. Okay so not only do Moses and Aaron and
Nadab and Abuhu who are not long for this world. That's right. That's right. Not only do
they see the God of Israel, right? But notice under his feet.
Hmm.
He describes this pavement under his feet, meaning he's standing.
And they're seeing feet.
Yes.
Feet on the ground.
Wait.
Right.
And it says he did not lay his hand on them.
He could have.
Yes, hands.
Right.
Which could have come into tactile contact.
Yeah.
Right with these people
Next example.
All right.
The next one is 1 Samuel chapter 3, verses 1 through 10.
Now the boy Samuel was ministering to the Lord in the presence of Eli, and the word of
the Lord was rare in those days.
Word of the Lord was rare in those days.
There was no frequent vision.
At that time Eli, whose eyesight had begun to grow dim so that he could not see, was
is lying down in his own
place. The lamp of God had not yet gone out, and Samuel was lying down in the temple
of the Lord where the ark of God was. Then the Lord called Samuel, and he said,
Here I am, and ran to Eli and said, Here I am for you called me, but he said, I did
not call lie down again, so he went and lay down. And the Lord called again, Samuel,
and Samuel arose and went to Eli and said, Here I am for you called me, but he said,
I did not call my son lie down again.
Now Samuel did not...
yet know the Lord, and the word of the Lord had not yet been revealed to him.
And the Lord called Samuel again the third time, and he rose and went to Eli and said,
Here I am, for you called me, then Eli perceived that the Lord was calling the boy. Therefore
Eli said to Samuel, Go lie down, and if he calls you, you shall say, Speak Lord for
your servant heirs. So Samuel went and lay down in his place. And the Lord came and stood,
calling as at other times.
Samuel, Samuel, and Samuel said, speak for your servant, heirs.
Notice God comes and stands in a particular place.
So the important part here is not just like he appeared in some kind of human form,
but then he stood, weight on feet on ground.
Yeah, right. And we're not going to read this part, but you could also think
of what he comes and stands on the rock before Moses strikes it.
Right.
Not just appearing above it, that just some form, you know, visible above it.
So the ones where the ones we're going through here specifically ones that have this kind
of material physicality.
Right.
So there are plenty of places.
Yes.
it just says God appears and you know
We can't prove even if he appears in some human looking way we can't there's not the tactile
Sense of weighted physicality but the ones we're talking about the ones we're going through here. We're going through because there is that sense
Right, there is a
materiality yeah, yeah
All right, the next one is from Jeremiah chapter one verses nine and ten so this is real short
Then the Lord put out his hand and touched my mouth and the Lord said to me
behold, I put my words in your mouth. See, I've set you this day over nations and over kingdoms
to pluck up and to break down, to destroy and to overthrow, to build and to plant.
Okay, so Lord puts out His hand and touches His mouth. There is physical contact.
Yeah, this is not just God put His words in my mouth. It's, I felt it, His hand.
Yes, yeah reached out. Yeah
And now, this next one is the real, we saved this one for last year, because this is the
one that really problematizes it the most.
Yeah, we've mentioned this many times.
So this is Genesis 18, verses 1 through 8.
And the Lord appeared to him by the oaks of Mamra, as he sat at the door of his tent in
the heat of the day, and this the he here, by the way, everybody's Abraham.
lift it up his eyes and looked and behold.
three men were standing in front of him. When he saw them, he ran from the tent-door to meet them
and bowed himself to the earth and said, O Lord, if I have found favor in your sight, do not pass by
your servant, let a little water be brought and wash your feet, and rest yourselves under the tree
while I bring a morsel of bread that you may refresh yourselves, and after that you may pass on since
you have come to your servant. So they said, do as you have said. And Abraham went quickly into the
attention to Sarah and said
quick, three sails of fine flour needed and make cakes. And Abraham ran to the herd and took
a calf tender and good and gave it to a young man who prepared it quickly. Then he took
curds and milk and the calf that he had prepared and set it before them. And he stood by them under
the tree while they ate. So you can wash dirt off of God's feet.
You know, and he eats.
Yeah, I have a question here and maybe you can, I don't know if this is a translation
thing.
I mean, if you keep reading, it's clear that this is Yahweh and two angels, right?
Because he sends to down, I think it's the beginning of chapter 19, if I recall,
there's about this ought to get lot.
It's a saga, right?
And it says that there are two angels.
It says that.
Yes.
So what is this by when it says here that they
He stood by them under the tree while they ate. Who's the day? Yeah, well it would be
I mean it's hard to fence that off right?
It's it's at least God could potentially be the angels
Okay somehow it's not ruled out by the text yeah, so it's just but they could also include Sarah and other people of the household right like
perhaps their standing
while he and you know even Abraham could be standing and eating. That could be included
in the in the day. Okay. Right. So if your question is just that include the angels, there's
no way to know for absolute. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. And I mean, the reason why I'm asking
that everybody is because you know, angels do not have material bodies. So generally speaking.
Yes, that's true.
Yeah.
We'll know.
So, yeah, but so the reason this really problematizes things is not just an abstract point of like,
well, wait a minute, because obviously someone could just say, well, if God wants to make himself tangible, he can make himself tangible.
God can do it every once, right? If he wants to make angels temporarily...
tangible and able to eat, you can do that, right?
And of course, we'd have to say yes, God can do whatever he wants, right?
But the problem is, in almost all of his post-resurrection appearances, I should say almost all,
in most of his post-resurrection appearances, Christ very deliberately eats something in
front of the apostles.
Yeah.
to prove that he's been raised from the dead bodily
and is not a spirit or a ghost.
So if the offenees, even his own appearances before the incarnation,
can eat. How does that work? Right?
see the problem here. Yeah. See the problematic thing here that we've made out of thought about before,
what we're reading about God eating in Genesis and then see Christ eating after the resurrection
appearances. Um, and then, you know, if we want to just punt, right, because we can find, of course,
if you've been to an Orthodox Church.
especially if you've been to Holy Week, you will hear a lot of things. You will hear at the
feet that the sinful woman washed with her tears were the same feet that walked in Eden.
Right? Yeah. Same feet. Just thrown out there. Yep. Right. We didn't make that up by the way
everybody we've mentioned that a bunch of times but we did not make that up that is in the
let's turn to Cascienae.
Sure, that's a big.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. So and plenty more where that came from. Yeah, right? Right?
Plenty more where that came from. That's just one example of many. So then
Okay, well
As weird as it seems, we'll just take the other route, right? It will say okay. Well
Jesus was always incarnate in some sense
That's right.
Jesus sort of eternal.
incarnate in some sense. Well then what does it mean when St. John said the word became flesh?
Yeah, the Creed says that he became man. Yeah, he was made man. Yeah.
What does that mean if we want to go the other way? Right? So there's not an easy out from this
problem.
Right? If we want to uphold all of these things as being true. And we have to
assume that since we're talking about some of the same church fathers and some
of the same videographers, we're affirming both of these things.
We're affirming both of these things. There's a particular point that we
celebrate on the Feast of the Anunciation.
Jesus the Messiah is conceived in the womb of the Thayer Tocos.
At that moment, he takes human flesh from her. We affirm that.
But we also affirm that this is him in the Old Testament. These are the same feet, same hands.
means the ones he received from the Théautocos.
Yep.
And by the way, since this is turning out to be a kind of short half, let me just throw this out here.
I haven't had a spicy take yet this episode. I don't feel like.
So here's today's spicy take.
All right. All right. Let's.
Almost no Protestants believe in the Virgin birth of Christ.
Oh.
Conservative Protestants believe in the Virgin conception of Christ.
right
right, but they don't believe that the theotokos was a virgin after giving birth.
Hmm. Right. Referring. There you go. Send your
angry letters to me, Father Andrew, and they should faith.
Yeah, yeah. What does Father Stephen mean by that? It's you ask yourself. Yeah, no,
it's I mean, you're obviously referring to her physical state, the physical state
I had her perpetual rigidity.
Yeah.
That's right. That's right. That's right.
Okay, well, that said...
About that note.
Yeah, we're gonna go ahead and take our second order.
Or if you're angry and want to call in, you can do that too.
And we'll be right back with the third half of this episode of The Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment.
Take your calls on the next part of The Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
Let's eat 558
F. Radio.
How do you explain the sacraments?
It's easy to say they're mysteries that we have to take on faith or on the authority
of tradition, but that is not how the early Christians understood them.
To them, and to all ancient people, the idea that physical objects had spiritual power
was very intuitive, whereas modern people tend to find this difficult, bizarre, or even
un-Christian.
This is because we live in an era.
shaped by secularism, a way of viewing a world that's incompatible with sacramental thinking.
Because secular ideas are at the heart of our culture, modern people tend to think in
secular ways without realizing it, even the most well-meaning of us.
How then do we live in, but not be of, a secular culture?
We need to understand the enchanted, sacramental way that the early Christians viewed the world,
but we also need to understand secularism.
What is it really?
Where did it come from?
how does it influence how we think about religion?
Journey to Reality, Sacramento Life in a secular age, breaks down these important issues
in accessible, non-academic language and is an ideal introduction for young readers,
catechumans and seekers, as well as for any Orthodox Christians who want to deepen their
understanding of the sacraments.
Journey to Reality, Sacramento Life in a secular age, by Zachary Porcou, now available at
store.EngineTfaith.com.
Again, that is store.EngineTfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, welcome back everybody. It's the third half. I know that when I bring back commercial for that video thing with you and Rick Rockingham because I love it.
That's true. It's a nice lawn. That's a lawn.
long trailer, I think it's like two, three minutes long.
By the day long, long, long, long, long trailer, though, speak, yes,
through speaking of Balthesia and his movie.
Seek speaking of Richard Roland, his wife just gave birth to their sixth child
today. So congratulations, Richard and Sophia. And and now Richard will start
getting a gazillion text messages from people, because I mentioned that here on
the podcast.
But I hear he hasn't named the baby yet.
So send him your suggestions.
No, he has.
He has
the suggestions.
Good name for the baby.
Yeah.
The third half, it's where everyone thinks we can't do math.
How could there be three halves?
Because it's a show and a half people, I keep telling you that.
Yes.
Yeah.
More than you bargain for more than you ever wanted.
More than you can stand.
So okay as is our want we finally get down to the question of exactly when
When does God became could become man since we've now
Exploded and problematized as the as as academics of the last. Everything's got problematic. Yes
We're all gassled. Yes
Yeah, so
What does that mean?
Because here's one of the problems.
If Jesus is God, any changes from sort of just God
into God-end man, isn't that what people kind of seem
to believe?
We're saying that God has changed.
But does God change?
So let me be clear.
God does a change.
Sorry.
Open theus, process theologians,
Higalians.
Et cetera. No, God does not change. Pretty clear in the Scriptures. Yeah. But yes, right?
Then that begs the question, does that include the Sun? Because it would seem like a divine
person taking on human nature at a
particular point in time would constitute a change. There's a before and an after and the after is different than the before.
Right.
On the other hand,
the epistle of the Hebrews tells us that Christ is the same yesterday, today and forever.
Yeah.
And our hemnography and our credal statements tell us that he was...
incarnate without change or alteration.
Yep. Or as I heard one amazing, amazingly bad translation say without flux.
Like I cannot sing the word flux.
I'm sorry.
Sands flux.
I know without flux.
Maybe just really hated Chris Chimneyl, Dr. Who.
Yeah. That's a big cut.
Yeah.
I'd love...
We uh...
Yeah, so the idea that
It sure sounds like a change or an alteration is obviously out there and needing to be countered
Yeah, right
And right where we say that God doesn't change
right we mean
the persons of the Holy Trinity don't change, right?
So someone could try to...
to get around that problem by saying, well, okay, right? Christ is a, my person, so there
was no change to Christ's divine nature when he took on human nature, right? So see,
God doesn't change. But that isn't cut it, right? Because when we talk about Christ, whether
quote unquote before or quote unquote after the incarnation.
talking about the person.
Yeah, natures don't do things.
Yeah, we're talking about the person.
We are not talking about one nature or the other.
We are saying, Christ doesn't change.
And by the way, this is a reminder.
Since we're bringing up the hemnography
and we're bringing up a lot of these things as sources,
you will sometimes in different fathers
different sources and a different hemnography.
See.
references to Christ taking a body, right, taking a body from the body of the
Theotokos. And remember, you gotta go way back in the way back machine on this
one to some of our earliest episodes, but remember what we talked about body
meaning in this context, right? That a body is in mexus of powers or potentialities.
And so body was the word that was used for
But we now more commonly use the term nature.
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
Nature's not really a biblical word.
Say Paul starts using it, but when say Paul starts using it,
he uses feces differently than the Greeks are using it at the time.
Yeah, yeah.
He means something different by it.
So, before we roll on, we actually do have a caller.
Yes, so Catherine is calling from Edmonton, Alberta.
So is this Catherine?
of the great white zaphone. Hello, father. Yes, this is Catherine from the great white zaphone. And I am
actually in the mountains of Alberta right now. So I remember.
I remember.
I met Catherine when I when I myself was in Alberta in Edmonton. So I yes, I recall you well.
So yeah, you wanted to say something about or
about father Steven's super spicy take there at the end of the second half.
Yes. Oh, I mean, I'm pretty much, I pretty much have my, my thumb on the call button,
the whole show. You know, and that was to me. That's all you needed to eat it over the break.
Yes. You know, like, but it's, it's an important thing because, you know, as a form of
Protestant.
like I'm becoming Orthodox now.
I just, I wonder why they believe that, you know,
Christ had, you know, he had brothers, yes,
James and stuff and whatnot.
But Protestants seem to miss
that Christ was adopted in a sense that Mary didn't have other sons.
She didn't bear other children.
And if Protestants are and this is
the spicy take. If they're so biblically orientated, why do they believe that Christ had other siblings
in the Bible? Yeah. I mean, there are people referred to as his brothers and sisters.
Yes, right and I think I mean honestly I think some of it is simply anti-catholic stuff right
you know, Catholics also believe in the ever virginity of Mary. And I think, you know,
a big piece of the way that I mean, I'm painting with a very broad brush right now, but a big piece
of perhaps. What's that? A roller perhaps. Yes, yes, exactly. Or, you know, like a spray gun of paint. But
But the way many Protestants regard the Virgin Mary.
is they're so, they're often so disturbed by allergic to unhappy with the Roman Catholic emphasis on the
veneration of the Virgin Mary that they try to downplay her significance as much as possible. And so one of
the ways that that's done is by saying, look, she's just an ordinary person, right? And so what would an ordinary
person who's just been married do have lots more kids.
Of course, you know, the typical, I haven't watched the new Netflix movie called Mary,
and I frankly don't intend to, but the pictures I've seen, the pictures I've seen, it's
the young couple of Mary and Joseph.
This is, this is a, it is a rancid pile of blasphemy.
Oh, you've seen it.
Okay.
Honestly, the only thing, the only thing that stopped me was that, that Joseph was young.
I was like, they got it wrong.
Yeah.
I see the person who's conscious has been seared by a hot iron.
It's like, fathers.
I think he even likes watching horror movies.
I think horror movies.
But yeah, I, you know, whereas, like I can't speak
from a Catholic point of view, but from an Orthodox point of view,
she is the new arc of the covenant.
She became the place that God dwelt bodily on earth,
set aside as a dwelling place for the Lord,
and that's for him alone, right?
So but as you said, there.
There is a big problem with looking at the brothers and sisters of Jesus and the
gospels and saying that these are children of Mary.
And that's because it doesn't ever say that they are her children.
It doesn't say that.
Not explicitly.
No, it doesn't even imply it.
There's no way that it says that they are her children.
Right?
They are called his brothers and sisters.
in Greek that the New Testament is written in.
And I mean, Father, you can mention the Hebrew, whether it's doesn't Hebrew too, but the word that's there for like brother, a veil for us.
And it's just a veil fee, I think, is for a sister.
Does not necessarily mean a child of my father and mother.
It can mean my cousin. It can mean my uncle, like the actual examples.
in the one key place, right?
The whole quote is, is this not the Carpenter's son, are these not his
brothers and sisters. Well, the answer to the first question is this not the Carpenter's
son is technically no. Right. Right. Right. Right. Like biologically no. Right. But but
so part of the issue here, there's a couple issues that come together because the Protestant
reformers did not deny this in any way. Luther believed to the Permanent Illusionary Calvin
And then of course, Calvary did.
Wingly did.
Yeah.
I think that's a lot of
the same. Uh, Bullinger,
Malanth, and we could keep
going. Yeah, we have the
receipts for all this. I
think even Martin Chemnitz.
Um, who is late as that? Uh,
so this is a much more modern
thing. Um, and, uh, I think
there is an element of what
father Andrew was was pointing
to of of Roman phobia, but, um,
it. The verse I want to delineate the issue between us because the way a lot of Protestants
will express this is, well look, I'm just reading what the Bible says. The most natural
way to read this is that they're his biological brothers and sisters, right? And I say,
okay, but you don't believe that. You don't believe that they had the same two parents
Jesus. Okay.
So you don't believe that that you believe that the way to read that is that they are his
half brothers and sisters.
I believe the way to read that is that they are his step brothers and sisters.
The text of the Bible by itself cannot resolve that.
Right.
Whether the word brother means half brother or step brother, right?
Can I ask something?
So you know, you know, in the point.
where it's like Jesus is saying, you know, who is my mother, who is my brother, who is my sister,
right? And they're freaking out and they're like, you're going to die, like, you know, like,
you're creating a problem here. And it's like, they know that he's the only son. I mean,
they know that he's the only son of Mary. So who's going to look after Mary, right? So if he gets
killed.
who's going to have his mother?
Well, you have Christ on the cross
to trusting his mother to St. John.
Yeah.
Why would he do that if St. James was right there?
Exactly.
One of the most pious Jewish men who ever lived
wouldn't take care of his own mother
unless he's not his mother.
Right.
There's a whole pile of things there
that don't make sense the other way.
But what I think honestly is motivating it
and the reason why
It's so much worse to be here now, and I think this comes out of puritanism.
You may be dimly aware that the Puritan's had a weird obsession with sex.
Being Canadian, I know, you know, it's different than it is for us down here, but here there's
this weird obsession with sex and Puritanism.
And when I say weird, I mean weird.
A lot of people don't know a lot of Puritan groups.
For example, couples got married in the nude in a closet.
But they put their hands out.
Yeah, weird stuff, weird stuff.
There's all the thing of bedfellows.
There's a lot of weird, pure stuff.
So that's exactly.
But this is really morphed into a culture wars thing now.
And the most common thing, I think, motivating this now when you talk to prizes, even
Geuckles about this is, and some of them will even say it to you, mostly guys, that it
would have been a sin for the Theo Toc-
refused to have sex with her husband.
Yeah.
Right.
But what the thing is though is that she wasn't married.
She was.
Right.
So this is being motivated by this weird culture war thing
of women don't have the right to deny sex to their husbands.
Yeah.
And they're protecting that out to the Theotokos.
It a fairly blasphemous way.
and end on
to Joseph in a pretty blasphemous way. Right. And so yeah, the yeah, I mean, part of it is that like
you know, like one of the big reasons that we've been doing this so for the last four years is
trying to help us all experience the world and see the world in a more enchanted way. Right. And
And if you don't look at this woman,
with the language that scripture uses to describe it, right, that she's the one that he should be called the son of the most high, that God himself is dwell inside her.
And that means something about her body, right? If you don't believe that there are holy places, then that's not going to make a sense.
You know, and then this is from the point of view of Joseph who like you're the tabernacle. What am I, you know?
know, if I can't enter into the holy of holies of the tabernacle or temple, I, how
am I, no, no, no, you know, right? That's how, that's how a person who has a sense of
secret secret. Never mind a building, let alone a human being. That's right. That's right.
Okay. Yeah. And that's a beautiful thing about, about pardon me, but that's the beautiful
thing about, you know, learning about the importance of her like we're
talking about, you know, God, God becoming a man. He became a man through Mary who was a woman
and had a body, and it's like the sanctity of her, of who she was. She was kind of a nun,
wasn't she? Yes. Like essentially. And she was supposed to be a nun, but she dedicated to God
but she was so blessed that she
gave
birth to God. I mean, like, why would you want to have no, like, I'm making a little joke here.
But why would you need to have, like, I mean, you, you can't have the best, you know, you're,
you're the most blessed for a reason, right? Why, why is there sort of the point of her, right?
Yep. And there's a skewed,
continued on the period is a period is a fact there's a there's a skewed
weirdly dysfunctional sexual ethic within most of evangelicalism.
Which I say this as a kid who spent a chunk of his adolescence listening to speeches
about how sex was the greatest thing in the world and just the ultimate most wonderful thing ever.
As long as you do it when you're married because if you do it before that you'll get a disease and die.
Yes.
Having that.
just over and over and over again. And that has made a lot of people who grew up around
that stuff, you know, who had Josh McDowell drumming that into their head or something.
Think that marriage is basically about having sex.
Especially I'm speaking as a man, right? Right? Adolescent men want to have sex. It is the worst
thing you can possibly do.
unless you get married and then it's wonderful and great and you could do it as much as you want.
And everything's good.
And that's not the real world.
I mean, in the end, you break it to any adolescent male.
Well, and that's not in fathers, you know, one thing. I don't mean to interject, but I do want to say that in the Orthodox Church, it's not, you know, you can do whatever you want now.
It's martyrdom.
No.
Right.
That's right.
And so a whole other gambit.
Right.
If you have a healthier view of what marriage is about, right?
Then the the the the the the Otoko's that take Joseph the Betroth make sense to you.
Yeah.
Yes.
If your view of marriage is that distorted dysfunctional one that's all based around sex permission
basically, then that bleeds into your view of
their marriage and you think that somehow, oh, well, that marriage is not a godly marriage
that if they're not having sex.
Yeah.
I mean, you know, right.
And you see how it gets warped around.
And so I'm not saying this to bash on them, right?
No.
Because like I said, they had this drummed into their heads as kids.
Well, and heck, I mean, they have a dysfunctional view now.
Frankly, Josh McDowell himself, who was very instrumental in a lot of that in particular
period.
He's not even a christ...
any more. You know, he kissed all that stuff goodbye, frankly, to use, you know, to riff on the title of his book.
Well, that's not Josh McDowell. That's another guy. Oh, who is that guy?
I have to look that up now. I can't say to be good bye guy. I don't know. Joshua Harris. Joshua Harris. Okay,
I'm sorry. I don't know whether Josh McDowell is to look Christian. I assume he is. Joshua Harris.
I roughly still lie. His son is a bit apologist but...
Joshua Harris who is left to Christianity. God bless him. But anyway, thank you very much for calling Catherine. It's a great top, which is actually related to a lot of this stuff in an oblique way.
About the incarnation, but I think it underlines more clearly what the incarnation is.
Yeah, well it is advent fathers so exactly about that about that so all right thank you
We're going.
Yeah.
So if you're an angry sex crazed evangelical send your hate mail to father Andrew.
Action faith back.
Oh Josh McDowell is still alive, but he's like 85.
It seems.
Yeah.
How about that?
Anyway.
Um, okay.
Yes.
So yeah.
Change.
So a lot of times body means nature.
Yes.
It very ancient and early writings.
So when it's talking about Christ taking a body, it's talking about Him.
taking human nature. Right. And so how could we say that Christ did this and he did this
at a certain point, but that when that happened, it was not a change. And it was true, quote
unquote, before that point. Yeah. Exactly. Well, so the first thing we have to say is that
Humanity
exists in time and space, like definitionally, right? Every human exists in time and space.
It's material. We have a material element to our being. Yeah, so the materiality that's
space, anything material exists in space time we've born, and that includes the fact that
Humans are born.
Yep.
There is a point in time and space at which humanity begins and there is a point in time
and space after, since the expulsion from paradise at which the human soul, the human life,
is separated from the human body that we call death.
Right, now of course we believe in the bodily resurrection.
But between birth and death for a human being, right, there is a bodily material existence
that takes place within space and time across a given span of time and you move through
space over the course of that period of time.
Therefore, if Christ takes upon Himself our humanity, our human nature, that means de facto.
Right.
De facto, he is going to have a birth.
He's going to be born of a woman.
Yeah.
Right.
At a point in time.
So he's going to be conceived.
Nine months later, give or take, he's going to be born.
Right.
He is going to live.
And although Christ was by nature not mortal, he voluntarily laid down his life.
Yeah.
Right?
Yes.
So there is this period, sometimes called Christ's earthly ministry, his earthly life, that
period between I would say, and this will probably be the thing that gets all the hate
mail, but that I would say goes from 3 BC to 30 AD or 80 30, right?
Yeah.
This 33 year period, Christ's earthly ministry is earthly life.
That is human life in time and space, right?
He has that, we didn't have that.
right then it would be hard to say he's human. Yeah right but he did so that's
part of what we mean by the incarnation right him take our human nature he has
that right now a note a little talk a little further about Christ's death and I'm
doing this because I've heard some things recently there are all kinds of things
Dear listener.
But I get into all this program.
that you think to yourself, wow, that's a weird rabbit hole. Father Steven is going down.
And I know just to be the weird pop culture sub references.
I haven't been a lot of those in this episode actually.
Oh, there have you just haven't gotten them.
I know.
So, um,
the, a lot of times, you know, I see things. I hear things.
off its stupid things.
And, you know, rather than just getting triggered in the moment and rant to get empty air like
the lunatic I am or going outside my house and yelling at passersby, oh, I wait.
I wait for this program.
I rant to all of you, the listeners.
This one's mostly related to what we're talking about, which is better than sometimes.
But it's several places in a weird synchronicity.
I've heard people trying to talk about the death of Christ theologically and saying all kinds of weird incoherent things.
Okay, so that's why I want to talk about this.
We talk Christ's birth, right? His conception is birth, the beginning, the ending, as we said, right? He's not mortal.
So what do we mean when we say Christ died?
What do we mean to say Christ died?
Because the discussion, there's all this stuff of like, well, did God die?
How could God die?
You're saying God died?
Right?
You'll get that from Muslim and Jewish folks, right?
And when they ask that question, it's not clear what they mean by the word died.
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean, for a human to die.
means that the soul is separated from the body.
Right. You're human soul is separated from your human body.
It does not mean. It does not mean.
I don't know why people seem to think that you see
to exist.
It does not mean that you see to exist.
Right. It never means that.
Right.
It never means that.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, when we say that our Lord Jesus Christ died on the cross,
We mean he died, his human soul.
was separated from his human body.
Yeah.
And sorry, Omni-Heretic William Lade Craig,
he had a human soul.
We covered this in 381.
That's right.
We had a council about this.
Yes, this is long settled, my friend.
Yes.
Um, right.
So Christ's human soul is separated from his human body.
His human body is placed in a grave.
is human soul.
goes down into sheol, down into hateys, to harrow it. And it is divinity. He's still everywhere.
Heaven and on earth, and in the regions under the earth, and on the throne with the father of the
spirit, the whole Shabbat. And the great with the body and hands with the soul's God. So
So, right now, this does not mean, or are you saying only his human nature does?
We're not talking about that.
This isn't where we talk about natures.
Natures don't die.
They don't do anything.
Okay.
No matter what, what would that mean?
Right.
When a human dies, his human nature doesn't die.
Well, and there's a lot being human.
There's one human nature that suggests that we're all dead.
Something.
Yeah.
The only way for human nature to die would be if you stopped being human.
Right, so maybe if you want to talk about that in terms of spiritual death or something as a metaphor, okay
But that's not what happens when someone dies, right?
They don't lose their nature. They aren't denatured
Okay
It would not say the divine nature obviously died on the cross because what would that even mean?
Right
So we're saying Christ human soul was separated from his human body and in the resurrection
Thank you.
They are restored.
Right?
Say we had our resurrection, our human body and our human soul will be reunited and restored
and renewed.
So that's what we're talking about.
Now you can say rhetorically, right, as some of our hymns do in Holy Week or things to
this effect, you can say God died on the cross.
Yeah
But what do you mean by that? You mean by that? Jesus is God and Jesus died on the cross. That's right.
We mean in the same way that we say that the Virgin Mary is the mother of God. Right. You're definitely
not saying the Father died on the cross. You're definitely not saying the Holy Spirit died on the cross.
You're not saying the divine nature or the divine essence died on the cross. None of these things
are coherent statements. Yeah. Okay. You are saying the person Jesus Christ died on the cross because
as its human soul was separate.
from a seward body, right? So the person Jesus Christ died on the cross. He is God,
air-go, transitive property, you can say God died on the cross. Just like with St. Peter
and Acts, refers to Christ's blood as God's blood, right? Christ's blood is God's blood,
is blood that belongs to God, but it's human blood. It's Christ's human blood that belongs to God
God and therefore is God's blood.
So anyway, I felt the need to clarify that in the face of chicaneery.
Right?
But that is to say, apropos of our topic tonight, Christ had a human conception.
I'll be an original one.
He had a human gestation.
He had a human birth.
Right?
Grue to physical maturity is
human and he died a human death, albeit voluntarily, right? He died a human death. But now that brings
us to the resurrection because what we're just talking about is the way humanity exists within time and
space, which is true, but humanity also exists outside of time and space.
Right?
You have to
affirm this unless you're a Sadducee.
Right.
If you, if you're going to say humanity doesn't exist outside of time and space,
let's see your Sadducee or an atheist, but I repeat myself.
Anyway, um,
because to say humanity does not exist outside time and space is to say there is
not, when you die, there's nothing afterwards.
There's nothing before conception.
there's nothing after death, right? Simply cease to exist in both directions. Human existence is confined to time and space. That of course is not what we believe as Christians.
Or people of most other religions, frankly, but so humanity also exists outside of time and space.
right, outside of the materiality of this world and this life, there is human existence.
Right?
And for...
us as Christians, this takes the form of resurrection. And this is not just the
resurrection on the last day, but St. John in Revelation will refer to the St.
Siglorians having experienced the first resurrection. Right, they have already
experience the first.
spiritual resurrection. The resurrection of the soul to God. Right? Because remember,
it's been a while since we repeated this, although we've repeated it a bunch of times on the show.
The John of Damascus, there's two kinds of death, physical death, separation of the human soul from
the human body, spiritual death, the separation of the human soul from God.
And so the first resurrection, the spiritual resurrection is the reconnection, the full
reconnection of the soul to God. This is what the saints have already
experienced. Okay, so they are now truly alive, not dead. Right? This is why Abraham,
Isaac and Jacob are alive, not dead. And Christ says what he's talking to the Sadducees
about it, he says to them, right, that the fact that Abraham, Isaac and Jacob are alive
is proof of the resurrection.
Suggesting they are resurrected.
Yes, and that's before his resurrection.
Right.
In terms of time and space.
The first resurrection.
Right.
And so, Christ's resurrection is the beginning of the bodily resurrection.
It reveals to us in so far as it has been revealed to us what our resurrection, our bodily
resurrection will be like and what resurrected humanity looks like.
what we see here.
very quickly in the resurrection appearances of Christ is that he is not inhabiting time
and space in the same way that we do on this side of the resurrection.
He can walk through doors.
He doesn't appear the same to people.
He appears to the midst of people, just all of a sudden.
Just suddenly, yeah.
This is not bound by time and space.
The fact that it's not bound by it.
Those are spatial examples.
The only added piece we're talking about here is the fact that it's also not bound by time.
And if it's not bound by time, it's not bound by time in either direction.
So we have the existence of Christ's humanity in time and space.
Right?
Roughly 3 BC to AD 30.
We have the existence of Christ, including his humanity outside of time and space.
After the resurrection, his resurrection.
Right?
And because that is outside of time and space, those feet can walk in the garden.
Now.
a little bit more evidence from the book of Revelation.
St. John, the Apostle, is having this vision.
In this vision, he sees famously 24 elders.
We've talked about how there's a couple pieces to what's going on here with their
24 elders. One of them is that 24 is one third of seven.
So Revelation 12, the devil cast down one third of the stars.
Right.
Let's say John sees these human elders, these human presbyters, human priests technically.
As part of the angelic host that is worshipping God in his God and Throne, that third that were swept out of the heavens have been replaced.
have it's been replaced.
to buy now these human saints 24 is also two sets of 12 the 12 patriarchs of the 12 tribe of
Israel and the 12 apostles right and there's a couple passages where they show up just quick passages.
Yeah yeah so you've got Revelation 4 4 where it says around the throne were 24 thrones and seated on
the thrones where 24 elders clothed in white garments with golden crowns.
on their heads. So there they are. And then also in Revelation 5 verses 8 through 10, we actually
hear from them and see them do some stuff. And when you had taken the scroll, the four living
creatures and the 24 elders fell down before the Lamb, each holding a harp and golden bowls full
of incense which are the prayers of the saints. And they sang a new song saying, where are you to
take the scroll into open at seals for you are slain and by your blood you ran some people
for God from every tribe in language and people in nation. And you have made them a kingdom
and priests to our God and they sharia on the earth. I seem to remember reading this translation,
which this is in the first person plural. We you've read some well, they're clearly talking
about themselves. Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, right because they're sitting on 24 throes, right? Right. Yeah.
with crowns other heads.
and they're the priests, right?
And they're the, yeah, the members of the kingdom, right?
So all that may be familiar to you.
But if you pause and think for a second,
if 12 of those 24 elders are the 12 apostles,
that means one of them is St. John.
He's seeing himself.
Yes.
He has a vision of himself.
And if you think that's a weird way to read this, I would refer you to what St. Paul says in Ephesians chapter 2 verse 6.
Yeah, by the way, I did just look up. It does say us there in the Greek. So this I was reading the ESV there by the way everybody.
So they tweaked it a little bit. Okay, Ephesians 2 6 and raised us up with him and seated us with him in the heavenly places in Christ Jesus.
But that's he Paul talking about himself.
Yes.
What are the apostles?
And that raised and seated right is in a Greek verbal tense that means it's accomplished
already.
So this brings us to sort of the locust that I know have at least referred to in this context.
the of Christ incarnation being both at a time but also being true outside of time and space,
and that is the reference in Revelation 13 verse 8.
Yeah, and so this by the way, and I'm going to read the King James for this one, and all the dwell
upon the earth shall worship him whose names are not
written in the book of life of the Lamb slain from the foundation of the world.
And the reason why I mentioned the King James because like this gets translated in other
ways, like sometimes they'll say, those whose names are not written from the foundation
of the world in the book of life of the Lamb slain.
And which is fiddling with the Greek.
Yeah, so is that a reasonable translation?
I mean, what's really going on there?
Right. It's translators.
you get the lamb having been slain from before the
foundation of the world and be like, well, that can't be
true because it happened at this point in time. Right.
They're reading in a linear way. Right. And they say, well,
that can't be it. So the book of life must be from before
the foundation of the world. Yeah. But grammatically,
that's not really consistent with what that's not really
consistent with what's going on there. Yeah. Number one.
Number two, despite what some people may tell you, if they've
We've only had one year of Greek work.
order is significant in Greek. And number three, if you understand how the book of life works,
that doesn't make any sense. Yeah. I mean, a Calvinist would love to be able to take it that way.
That God filled everybody into the book of life before the world was created.
The first thing that's done is he publishes this book. But all you got to do is go through the
the scripture and look at places where it talks about people being blotted out of
book of life. That's right. Right. And we've talked about on the show before the book of life
be connected to these heavenly talents ideas that this is these are the books that are recording the
things that happened that unfold in creation. So the idea that the names were all written in it before
the creation doesn't make any sense in terms of how the book of life was understood. Right. Even
even if you did warp the text to put it that way.
So that
dog don't hunt. Right? Yeah. The Greek is not really ambiguous here.
Enough to do that. And again, it conceptually doesn't work.
Another way that people have tried to take this is to understand, well, the lambs
lane from the foundation of the world, this is how well, there's this plan. God has a plan
that involves Christ offering himself, sacrificial, on the cross, and the plan is from before
the foundation of the world because God
was sitting back there in the past and he knew what would happen in the future.
And so he came up with a plan.
Does anyone see the problem here?
Yeah.
God is not a material thing that occupies time and space.
Right.
He knows all at once.
Yes.
It would be right.
So that is it makes sense either.
Right.
What is being said here by St. John.
Right. Is that crime?
self offering on the cross, which obviously intimately involves his humanity. Right? It's what makes it possible.
So Christ, the second person of the Trinity, having taken a part of self-art human nature, his self offering on the cross.
This is the basis for the creation of everything in the universe.
Hmm.
And this is.
is the purpose of the creation of everything of the universe.
As St. Paul says about Christ through whom and for whom are all things created.
Yeah.
And I mean, St. John essentially says the same thing in the prologue of his gospel.
And Christ says, I am the Alpha and the Omega.
Right.
The basis of the purpose, the telos, the beginning and the end.
L
the Omega, right? That's what St. John is saying. And this is all over the New Testament if you
look for it, right? Like I said, St. Paul has it. St. John has this as a major theme as we just said,
right? So the incarnation, Christ's humanity is a fact of creation. It is the
goal it is the purpose it is the whole thing right it is the whole thing is what say Maximus is
getting at with the logos and the the log of creation all being connected to him okay uh
Christ stands at the center so this isn't a plan god came up with to deal with human sin
Yeah, it's not plan B.
Right? This isn't anything like that. Right? This is the whole game plan. Right? God created
a world, a universe, and he created people to share his love with. Right? And the way
he does both of those things, the way he creates, the way he reveals himself, the way he
shows his love is through.
the humanity of Christ through the incarnation of Christ. That's how it happens.
And the only way we come to know God is in the person of the incarnate Jesus Christ.
That's not just true since he was born, circa 3 BC.
That's true.
in the Old Testament. Say, Chad said, no one has seen the Father, the only begotten, or
the unique son, the unique God, so he can put them as made him known. But that's also true
to go back a few episodes, right? Christ was the way that your primitive hunter-gatherers
and the Neolithic era came to know God. He is the way in which God is inscribed in
creation in the sky they looked at at night, the ground they forged for food, the love they shared
with their families, right? Christ was inscribed in all of that. And that's how they came to
Newt, no God in how to find salvation. So the incarnation is at the center of everything,
Right, but goes beyond just...
This world's materiality and our understanding of the flow of time and the limits of space.
So to wrap things up here, if you happen to be watching this or listening really to this
episode via YouTube or you've seen the promo images.
for this particular episode, the icon that's in that image is the creation of Adam.
And if you look at it, you can see on the left is Christ.
And on the right, and slightly below him, is Adam.
And you can see Christ breathing the breath of life into Adam.
There's a really interesting detail.
If you look closely at this icon and
You may not notice this unless someone points this out to you, but you might also notice
it for yourself.
Once you see it, you can't unsee it.
And that is that God in the flesh, in this icon of the creation of Adam, his face and Adam's
face are the same face.
So what is going on with that?
Well, man is made in the image of
God or as it says in the Greek text of Genesis, he's made according to the image of God.
And this is depicted in icons quite literally.
Well, who is the image of God?
Christ is the image of God.
He is the image of the invisible father.
And so if Adam, if humanity is made according to his image, it makes sense to depict that in
I caught in terms of Adam looking just like Jesus.
like Jesus. And it's Jesus in the psychon. It is very clearly Jesus. You know, this is not the
faceless Jack chick Christ. This is Jesus. And that is a very profound icon in light of everything
we've just said for the last two and a half hours. So if Christ...
the incarnate Christ is the basis of creation and the purpose of creation.
And he makes us, according to him, according to him, he who is the image of God, what does
that say about humanity vis-à-vis the whole creation?
means that this whole creation is summed up in humanity.
And that when we talk in Christianity about mankind being the pinnacle of creation, the center of creation, the priest of creation, all of this stuff,
it's because we are made according to Christ.
It's not like a special status.
You know, God made all these creatures and said, oh, I like this one. I'll make him the chief of everything.
No, it's that baked into the very nature of you.
Christianity is that we are meant to be in Christ.
The Christ who created all things, the Christ through whom all things were created, the Christ
for whom all things were created, the Christ slain from the foundation of the world, the
Christ who is enthroned in glory and we are invited to sit on thrones next to His, that
Christ, the one and only Christ, Jesus, the Son of God, the Son and Word of God.
That's the purpose of humanity.
That's our very purpose, right?
Someone was asking in the YouTube chat, like, what does this have to do with our salvation?
It has everything to do with our salvation.
Because salvation is not just where do I go when I die.
Like, one of the themes we've talked about for the last four plus years in this podcast
is the destiny of you.
humanity in Christ. And that destiny is to be, as St. Paul said, seated in the
high places with him. That destiny is to be glorified, to become by grace, what
he is by nature, to become one of my favorite verses, Luke 20, 36 Jesus, himself
says, sons of God equal to the angels, sons of the resurrection.
Right.
And all of this is apparent in this icon of God making Adam, of Christ making Adam, and you see they have the same face.
They have the same face.
All of this is there. If you understand then, this aspect of the incarnation that we've been talking about for this episode,
I hope it will drive you to repentance.
You know repent for the kingdom of God
is at hand, that's what the kingdom of God is. That's what the kingdom of God is. And
our repentance is moving towards being worthy of that. We don't make ourselves worthy. It's
Christ who made us who makes us worthy. But he gives us the way to receive that from him. He
It gives us the way to live.
The way to repent.
This faithfulness is a gift from God.
We didn't come up with it ourselves, St. Paul says that.
And therefore, it's through that faithfulness, by grace, that we are saved.
So I feel like I say this at the end of a lot of episodes, but far from this being about
sort of speculating on weird esoteric pident.
theological minutiae. This once again goes to the right, the heart of what it means to be Christians.
And it is the Alphan the Omega in the Scriptures itself, Genesis to Revelation, but most especially in the face of
of Jesus Christ our true God, our Savior, the Redeemer of our souls.
So that's, that's what all this means to me.
So, yeah, you brought up so many assholes this has to do with their salvation.
So this particular episode, I hope you didn't learn anything.
And uh, I hope it is of no practice.
value to you. And I hope it doesn't help you with your repentance or your salvation.
I want it to do something else during this nativity season where we're celebrating
Christ's incarnation. Because I think there's one thing needful for a lot of us.
And as always, when I say these kind of things, I'm including myself.
right? We want to learn things and we want to understand things. We could become
obsessed sometimes as a point of script velocity with our own sand and
repentance working out our own salvation.
and obsessed with the practical matters of living the community.
All of which are important.
But I think there's also an important place
moving past all that work and all that toil
and all those very important things day to day
for awe directed toward God.
toward awe and admiration directed toward our Lord Jesus Christ,
for who He is and what He has done for us.
And this is very much available to us in our Orthodox worship.
If we're looking for it, if we're not doodling around in a copy of the service text,
stacks trying to understand it and trying to record.
I'll just say that I'm not going to decide this statement on this page with that statement over there. Well, those big sets together.
They were not obsessed with the fact that we, you know, got cut off and cut somebody out on the way to church.
And we feel guilty about it. And if we could sit on those things aside for a minute.
touch with who God is and what He has done and who Christ is and what He has done.
which goes so far beyond what we can comprehend,
what we can reason about, what we could explain with some cool proof texts and fancy logical arguments.
That leaves, what is one of my favorite verses of the Acophysed to the Theotokos, that leaves the Philosopher's Voiceless Fish.
Right. Just being in wrapped off for a while.
That's what I hope thinking about some of the things.
Some of the brain hurts things.
Some of the things that don't quite make sense.
Some of the things that make us nervous
that we talked about in this episode.
That's the effect I hope it will have for me
and for our listeners tonight.
There'll be some moment here.
So we approach nativity,
as we celebrate the feast.
Whereas with with family celebrating the feast and friends, we will have that moment of just wrapped awe
Where we stop trying to understand and explain
And we stop worrying about ourselves and we stop worrying about the day-to-day things of this life
And just sit or stand in wonder
wonder at the God who created us.
and the destiny that he created us for.
That's where I'm aiming
with this episode.
That's why I think we sometimes need to talk
about things that are past the limit
of what we can really understand
and push past that barrier.
So that's my hope.
Our next episode is going to be pre-recorded.
But so this is the last time before an activity
I'm going to talk to you guys live.
But that's my, that's my Christmas wish for you.
Amen.
Well, that's our show for tonight, everybody.
Thanks for tuning in.
If you didn't happen to get through to us live,
we'd still like to hear from you.
You can email us at LordofSpiritsandAncients.com.
You can message us on our Facebook page.
You can also leave us a voice mail
at SpeakPipe.com slash LordofSpirits.
That's where we're gonna do our next episode,
by the way, as those voice mail.
And if you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity,
you need help to find an actual 3D
parish, head over to orthodoxintro.org.
Join us for our live broadcast of the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern
4 p.m. Pacific.
He faces forward, trading in his blindness for the world of love.
Time is raging.
May a raging vein.
And if you use Facebook, you can follow our page.
You can join our discussion group.
And please review and rate this podcast wherever it is you happen to listen to it and share
it with a friend who is going to benefit from it.
Riley be sure to go to
Thank you.
Good night.
Kupus.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of Ancient Faith
Radio.
I'd be held and I heard the
voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts and the elders and
the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of thousands saying
with a loud voice worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches
and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing. Revelation chapter 5
verses 11 through 12.